# 大家好
Hi everyone!
# 現在這個花生熟啦 這玉米也熟啦
Now the peanuts here are ripe, and so are the corns.
# 我撴一下那太陽傘 大熱這啦天氣
I'm trying to stand an umbrella here. It's too hot now.
# 我順便拔一點回去 回去煮
I'll then pick some back home, and then cook them.
# 這攝影小哥家的 我家今年 今年沒種
These are Mr. Cameraman's peanuts. I haven't, haven't grown any this year.
# 我不用種 左隣右舍都種了很多
I don't need to. Everybody next to me is already growing a lot.
# 到前面去 它怎麼斜在這
Let me go to the front. Why isn't it standing upright?
# 誒呦 小朋友
Aya! Kid!
# 你看 這太陽傘立好啦
Look! This umbrella is alright now.
# 這樣就可以躲一下太陽 就沒有那麼熱
Then we can have a shelter, and it's not so hot now.
# 誒 桶呢
Eh? Where's my bucket?
# 搞點花生 用來煮著吃
Pick some peanuts, then we can cook them.
# 很好吃的哦
It's really tasty, you know.
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 你看
Look!
# 粒粒飽滿 好多啊
Round and full. A lot!
# 這花生就是拔好拔 但摘的時候不好摘
The peanuts, pulling them out is easy. But picking them off is a headache.
# 要一個一個摘
They need to be picked one by one.
# 好多哦
A lot!
# 要下了雨來拔應該很好拔
It should be much easier after rain.
# 趕緊來幫忙
Come and help us! C'mon!
# 這是我的
This is mine.
# 你看我多麼粗暴的拔
See how rough I'm picking them?
# 我都在拔呢
I'm also picking.
# 你在拔是不是 嗯
You're picking, aren't you?
Um!
# 好啊 等下你多吃兩個啊
Good! Eat more in a while, alright?
# 這個草來的
This is weed.
# 啊 太熱啦 你看 全身都是汗
Ah! It's too hot! Look! I'm soaked with sweat.
# 我下去河 河裡面泡一下 受不了啦
Let me go, go into the river. I can't stand anymore.
# 啊 你看這個水潭
Ah! Have a look at this pond!
# 這個水潭舒服的哦
This pond is really nice, you know.
# 啊 舒服
Ah! Cool!
# 誒 這個淺噠
Eh? Why is it so shallow?
# 這裡就深一點 這裡你看 全部 下面全部是沙子
It's a bit deeper here. Here, look, it's all, all sand at the bottom.
# 在水裡泡一下舒服多啦
Soaking in the water, makes me feel so much better.
# 現在最少三十六度以上哦
I think it's now at least thirty six degrees.
# 要不要下來哦
You wanna come down?
# 不要拍啦 下來
Come down! Don't film anymore!
# 嗯~太淺啦這裡 找個深一點的地方
Um~ The water is too shallow here. Let me find a deeper spot.
# 誒 剛好從 可以從這裡過
Eh? I can pass, pass right from here.
# 哇 這 全身泡在水裡很舒服的哦
Wa! It's, you know, soaking the whole body in the water is really great.
# 全身都涼爽一下 你看 我兒子也來了
It cools every inch of my skin. Look! My son is also coming.
# 我厲害吧
Am I marvellous?
# 爸爸再遊回去 你看
Daddy is gonna swim back there, look!
# 剛遊完泳是吧 全身清爽是吧 搞幾個西瓜來吃
After swimming, the whole body is cool. Let's fetch some watermelons.
# 去兄弟家 他家西瓜熟啦 剛才叫我去
Let's go to my buddy's place. His watermelons are ripe now and he just asked me to go.
# 走 帶你們去摘西瓜
Let's go! Come with me to pick watermelons!
# 帶你們去 摘西瓜 走
Come with me, to pick watermelons. Let's go!
# 你看 掏出來啦 兄弟幫我把它搞 搞出來的
Look! We've taken it out! My buddy helped me bring it, bring it out.
# 那裡修路 過不去
There's roadwork. We can't pass.
# 這裡一袋 那輛車還有一袋 這還有兩個
Here's a bag. There's another bag in the other car. Two more are coming.
# 這還有兩個
Here are two more.
# 你看 就摘了那麼一丟丟 太熱啦
Look! We've just picked a tiny little bit here. It's too hot.
# 等下雨的時候我再去拔
I'll go again when it rains.
# 差不多啦 夠啦
Alright! It's enough.
# 經常煮這一個來吃 要洗乾淨來
We'll make it very often. Let's wash them first.
# 你看 搓兩下就幹淨啦 這花生
Look! Squeeze them a couple of time and its cleansed, the peanuts.
# 這水 把這個水
The water, pour out,
# 倒掉
the water.
# 這個花生都是種下去就沒人管了
After planting, nobody has ever taken care of the peanuts.
# 我去看了一下 還沒死
Then I took a look and they were still alive.
# 現在就長了那麼多
And now so many have grown.
# 來 加點鹽下去就好啦
Alright! Put some salt and that's it.
# 夠了 夠了
Enough, enough
# 可以
Alright!
# 好啦 開始煮啦
Alright! Let's start cooking.
# 要煮差不多一個多小時就可以吃啦
Cook it for around an hour and something, then we can eat.
# 好 我們就等一等
Alright! Let's wait.
# 你看 這兩條繩子拴着它 就可以放養啦
Look! With these two leashes, I can let them walk around now.
# 如果不拴著它 它全跑的哦
They would run away, if they're not tethered, you know.
# 要拴一個月左右才放 要不然不放
I'm gonna tether them for a month, before I can let them run around freely.
# 跑了就太可惜了
It would be too bad if they run away.
# 上次找這兩隻 找 找那隻黑色那隻羊
Last time I looked for the two, looked, looked for the, for the black goat.
# 找的太辛苦啦
It was killing me.
# 嘿呦
Heyo!
# 一看到我就跑
They run away once they see me.
# 管它嘞 讓它們吃飽來
Leave them alone, and let them eat as much as they like.
# 讓它清理一下這些草也好
It's nice to let them clear some of the weed here.
# 晚上再把它牽回去
I'm gonna take them back to the shed at night.
# 這個熟了哦這個
It's done now, the peanuts.
# 把它抬出來
Let me take it out there.
# 好燙
Hot!
# 你看這個花生熟了
Look! The peanuts are done now.
# 很香的哦
It smells really good, you know.
# 有點燙
It's a bit hot.
# 剛起鍋的
It's just taken away from the heat.
# 好像差了點鹽
It seems that the salt is not quite enough.
# 哇 好香啊
Wa! It smells wonderful!
# 好香啊 太燙了哦
It's good. Too hot, isn't it?
# 好不好吃
Does it taste good?
# 不要怕燙
Never mind the heat
# 沒事啊 不燙了不燙了 不燙吼
It's fine. It's not hot, it's not hot, it's not hot anymore.
# 嗯 好糯啊
Um! It's soft and mushy.
# 好不好吃刘星辰
Does it taste good? Liu Xingchen.
# 好吃
Yup!
Indeed
# 家裡好玩還是縣城好玩
Where do you like more? In the village or in the county seat?
# 家裡
In the village
# 家裡好玩哦 又可以去游泳 是不是
Yea, in the village. And you can go swimming too, right?
# 嗯
Um!
# 縣城 只能關在家裡
In the county seat, I can only stay at home.
# 只能關在家裡是不是
You can only stay at home, right?
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 帶小孩
I gotta take care of the kids.